<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://isimo00.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://isimo00.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-04T05:39:20+00:00</updated><id>https://isimo00.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal webpage of Irene Simó Muñoz </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://isimo00.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://isimo00.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://isimo00.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Random Hyperbolic Graphs and social networks</title><link href="https://isimo00.github.io/blog/1990/rhgs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Random Hyperbolic Graphs and social networks"/><published>1990-01-01T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>1990-01-01T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://isimo00.github.io/blog/1990/rhgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://isimo00.github.io/blog/1990/rhgs/"><![CDATA[<p>How to synthesize graphs that are high-fidelity representations of real social networks has been a question for quite some time. There are a few very popoular - even classic, at this point - approaches, notably the Erdos-Renyi, Barábasi-Albert or Watts-Strogatz models. The literature on any of these three is so large and rich that there’s no possible way I could provide a better explanation or intuition of their mechanics than anything already out there. However, it is worth mentioning why none of these are perfect models, and why RHGs can outperform them in quality in some aspects.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My intuitive notes on RGHs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gossiping in social networks</title><link href="https://isimo00.github.io/blog/1990/social-dynamics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gossiping in social networks"/><published>1990-01-01T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>1990-01-01T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://isimo00.github.io/blog/1990/social-dynamics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://isimo00.github.io/blog/1990/social-dynamics/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="gerrymandering-or-political-districting">Gerrymandering or Political Districting</h1> <p>I have modelled this problem from three different perpsectives:</p> <ol> <li>Creating an heuristic that finds a gerrymandered solution given an initial district map</li> <li>Defining a combinatorial (optimization) problem with a SAT formulation</li> <li>Defining game theory dynamic</li> </ol> <h1 id="gossiping">Gossiping</h1> <p>The gossiping problem was proposed originally as follows \cite{baker1972gossips}:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>There are $n$ ladies, and each of them knows some item of gossip not known to the others. They communicate by telephone, and whenever one lady calls another, they tell each other all that they know at that time. How many calls are required before each gossip knows everything?
</code></pre></div></div> <p>If we set the number of gossips to 1, this is equivalent to broadcasting. Now, intuitively, celebrities or <strong>influencers</strong> should be the most effective sources of gossip to optimize the spread speed, right? But if we are trying to promote our friend’s business, getting a “big” celebrity to talk about it might be unfeasible. Rather, we could think of contacting a few, less-known micro-celebrities. Maybe if we do that skillfully enough, we might be even able to spread our message even faster than if we contacted the big celebrity to begin with!</p> <p>We want to focus on this new optimization problem. How many, how popular celebrities would be optimal for our gossiping or broadcasting scenario?</p> <p>We will define the cost of getting someone to spread our gossip as their degree.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some informal exploration of gossip spread using Random Hyperbolic Graphs (RGHs)]]></summary></entry></feed>